um
hello and welcome everyone it's January
11 2023 we're in active bookstream
number 1.1 on governing continuous
transformation off to the facilitator
all right so today we are discussing
part one of governing continuous
transformation we're lucky enough to
have the author Bajan kesri with us
today I hope I pronounce that right yeah
all right wonderful wonderful um so we
are the active inference Institute so we
are participatory online Institute that
is communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference all those links
are socials so this is recorded in a
live stream and an archived live stream
so please give us feedback so we can
improve our work uh all backgrounds and
perspectives are welcome and we will be
doing our best to follow a video
etiquette for this live stream
all right so this is a all active
inference Institute activities are
participatory so if you want to get
involved let us know
all right so this is the 1.1 book stream
so we've been discussing uh governing
continuous transformation reframing the
strategy governance conversation by John
kosri uh so we've over the past four
live streams we've been discussing part
one of the book section by section uh
and it's been very methodical unpacking
the concepts and today we're lucky
enough to have Bajan with us uh in
person where we're going to be actually
kind of unpacking some of those hairy
Concepts or questions that came up
during those previous four live streams
so if you haven't seen those previous
four live streams definitely recommend
uh watching those or better yet reading
the book and that would be some
important context all right so let's go
into it so before we get started let's
just do some quick intros so I can start
this off so let's do like an intro and
then we quickly just say what you're
excited about today
all right so my name is Tyler I'm uh a I
work in Dow governance and protocol
design in a previous life I also was a
strategy consultant at you know large
corporation so
organizational change is something I'm
very personally passionate about and I'm
really excited to kind of dive into some
of these thornier questions that came up
over the previous four live streams are
very happy to have uh John with us here
today
I'll pass it off to Blue
um blue night I am an independent
research consultant in New Mexico my
background is largely Neuroscience but I
am a founding member and on the board of
directors here at the Active inference
Institute so I'm very excited to kind of
get the perspective of free energy
governance like we are the African
friends Institute we should be using
free energy governance in the way that
we kind of Drive our Institute forward
and our with our board and our
governance method so I'm excited to just
be studying this concept and learning
how to best apply it to my work here at
the Institute and I'll pass it off to
Daniel
hey I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California looking forward to the
conversation today to continuing to
develop our relationship with the work
and just to check in periodically as the
niche continues to develop so rapidly
which is a focus of free energy
governance so Bijon to you
okay so I should address the very same
questions
uh well obviously
um you know in in in life everything is
is is very past dependent so uh I happen
to actually a very young age go on the
board of directors of public companies
and
as a result of it I was always
fascinated actually how companies are
being governed and I was many times also
astonished about the fact how
disconnected the very top of the company
where all the decision power resides uh
is disconnected actually from the um
from the front line of the of the
company I do recall actually one of the
uh boards I have joined in 2019 very
exciting company took a it's a difficult
name to pronounce but it's a global
leader in Innovation Services we do
really fascinating projects around the
world and when I introduced myself I
said
there's really all the intelligence in a
firm is really at the bottom it's not at
the top so that was obviously very
surprising for board members to listen
to because there's a very
self-understanding of board members is
that they are the smartest guys in the
room and that they obviously are
entrusted by the stakeholders was
allocating all the resources so I I'm
really excited about how
the role of the board has to change in a
world which is and has become
increasingly discontinuous very
distributed where a bunch of very smart
guys meeting up four to eight times a
year to take all the key decisions in
the company
um it's not in my view a recipe for
sustainable success
and that has obviously led to the fact
that many times
CEOs become very very powerful and the
board is there to guide to advise
um to approve uh and to make sure kind
of things are more or less in order but
I think
like with everything with every person
with every process it's a little bit
like flipping the coin I mean as much as
certain things or certain people explain
success they eventually also explain
failure
and the idea really behind the free
energy governance concept and inspired
obviously by Kyle fresen's free energy
principle is
um
when you look at biology you look at
nature you start understanding there's a
lot of self-organizing mechanisms which
determine the survival of an organism
and my idea and the the the drive behind
free energy governance is really we
should be revisiting a number of
self-organizing principles to make the
company actually much more
resilient
in discontinuous and distributed Market
environments
um
I'm just looking at the questions the
other questions I mean that's certainly
something I'm excited about that's in a
nutshell really what has been inspiring
uh from my background and from uh from a
theoretical point of view uh the free
energy governance concept
um and I do think uh uh and that's why
I'm looking really forward uh to this
session and I really appreciate the
diligence with which you have prepared
it and the questions that when I talk
about the free energy governance concept
people get it because there's really
three simple Dimensions there's a
structural Dimension which very strongly
inspired from neurosciences but how do
we connect actually our prefrontal
cortex with the nervous system and how
is it an interactive top-down buttermark
connectivity which has to work and you
can transpose this onto organizations
and you can very quickly see there's
tremendous friction in an organization
because the bottom at the top uh don't
really
interact and connect the way our nervous
system and our brain that's the second
dimension is uh this Dimension I call
cognition but what it really means is
rather than teaching uh uh uh adaptation
which is really the dominant school it
it it it it MBA programs we should be
analyzing the environment and then adapt
accordingly I say the world and strategy
is not environment driven but it's
interpretation driven so when you take a
more interpretation-driven approach you
are much more in power to create
actually your own
I don't like the word reality because
that's a very relative concept but
you create your own Eco Niche and the
equal Niche you really want to compete
in so I do believe we are much more in
power than we resist to believe
in the third dimension is related to
capabilities and capabilities
um uh is a big Topic in in management
science obviously
um capabilities at the board level
haven't been really addressed and my
work on the free energy governance side
is trying to develop capabilities at the
board level in certain meta capabilities
and that really leads into the topic
when we say in the distributed and
discontinuous world how does the board
has to evolve in order to be meaningful
it's either going to be completely
irrelevant it could be potentially a
source of inertia or it can
allow the company to prosper and to
outperform its its competitors I guess
for this slide
I wouldn't say much more
awesome there's a lot to dig into there
and so we'll get to some of those those
bigger topics in a second here
um all right so this is where we're at
in the book we've been reading part one
um up to now which is a lot about
framing the conversation about what free
energy governance is in the free
interview principle and right now we're
at the conclusion so we'll read the
abstract for that in a second here
all right so the room after today today
is a discussion around these seven
questions in the beginning of the
discussion we'll be talking more about
like really how do you communicate with
free energy governance is and then later
in the discussion we'll be really more
getting into some of the the
nitty-gritty questions about maybe some
of the implementation of what free
energy governance can look like
um and we'll keep it free-flowing today
I mean we'll try to all these questions
if we get off on the tangent that's
actually totally fine and we can just
kind of take the conversation where it
goes
very good um please
oh sorry we'll we'll just we'll start
off by reading the uh the abstract and
then we'll kind of get into the
discussion but is there something that
you want to say before we move on no no
no no no I I I follow you okay great so
uh blue do you want to read the slide
for us
sure uh is that all that's on the slide
there's one more okay strategic renewal
research is now confronted with
important challenges concerning process
design cognition and dynamic
capabilities sensing and sense making of
relevant signals as a basis for
initiating strategic renewal are
appreciated by an action-centric and
explorative engagement with the world we
are moving from co-aligning organization
with environment in form of adaptation
to co-creation as firms build agility
through distinctive environmental
enactments all existing Frameworks and
studies in corporate governance as well
as strategic cognition remain
characterized by one or a combination of
the following fundamental limitations
cool and I could take this slide so uh
one the environment and environmental
change are generally treated as
objective reality to strategic renewals
treated as a top-down content rather
than top-down bottom-up process
challenge strategic renewal study that
the managerial level but only marginally
at the board level formal processes are
the focal unit of analysis and five
demographic and universally measurable
variables dominate with no new
consideration for strategy relevant meta
capabilities at the board level
prediction governance introduces a novel
across hierarchical gender that
infrancentric framework empowering the
firm as a generative model of its
econation shareholders and board
directors must interpret the board's
strategic relevance and discontinuous
world if not the board is prone to turn
into or remain a source of inertia
compromising uh firm performance and
survival
all right let's get into it
so uh the first question here is just
you know creation governance as we've
been going through this last uh you know
four live streams it can get very deep
right there's like a thermite
thermodynamic angle to it there's an
information Theory angle there's a
machine learning angle right so you can
go down the rabbit hole and you can go
very far but at the end of the day too
like there's a very intuitive way you
can think about free energy governance
and so I'm curious when you meet
Executives other Business Leaders and
you have to communicate what free energy
governance and the free interview
principled are how do you succinctly
communicate that communicate hey this is
different from what you're already doing
when you look at uh
what has been happening uh in the last
20 30 years we see that
um technology is not only building
incredible connections but we also do
see that the cost of innovation is
coming quite dramatically down if you
take a startup in Silicon Valley in the
1990s
to build something that say which would
take a million dollars at the time you
can probably do it today with ten
thousand dollars the same bit
so the power of the individual
in creating new stuff changing the way
we consume
product wise
um has increased dramatically as a
result of it this continuity has been
rising dramatically apart from that the
world has obviously also again thanks to
technology become quite uh connected and
integrated now when you look at all that
stuff what technology is doing what
individuals are doing they don't even
need to be incorporated
it's creating a lot of change in the
resource Market in the resource Market
is really
I don't like actually I do not like the
term top environment
probably the bottom certainly is much
more Frontline
um the top yes usually the top is the
board because these are the the last
guys the ultimate people taking into the
the resource allocation decision on big
topics which concern the entire firm but
when you look at
all the stuff that is happening right
now
in product markets in Supply chains in
universities
um where there is great thinking there's
not only great ideas there's new
products coming out and you start
looking at the guys who are sitting in
the board of a big company they are so
far removed
from really being connected to what can
happen now and that's very natural
because they there's only as much
attention we have as much cognitive
bandwidth we have and how much can they
process
the bigger problem however is and I
would say to your first question what's
the hook is
every board member every CEO
would love and they
there's a wonderful concept which is
called skilled incompetence and skilled
incompetence really means people are
doing actions which are counter
productive to what they really want to
achieve and
sea level board members are really keen
on understanding what's happening in all
these markets and catching up on all the
impulses inspiration in order to think
about where should our organization be
going but inadvertently they're creating
a lot of friction and they're bringing
themselves far more removed so the Big
Challenge and this is really what free
energy governance is addressing how can
we connect the top at the bottom in a
much more efficient way and that has a
lot of challenges because you have
middle management how is information
traveling but a much more interesting
thickness which is happening right now
is when you look at artificial
intelligence
artificial intelligence
effectively allows you to decouple
two things which usually came as a Unity
it is
the prediction and the Judgment which
together form a decision
so when you look at the anatomy of a
decision consisting of prediction and of
judgment
with the increasing deployment of
artificial intelligence that is being
actually decoupled now
what that means is that the value of
human judgment becomes much more
important
but then the question does arise
who is best positioned to make the
judgment is it really the sea level is
it at the very top once I have all the
AI prediction available and I can
generally grade predictions as an input
into my decision making and subjected to
judgment so all of a sudden you have to
very carefully think what should be and
continue to be decided at the very top
and what should be
not reach the top any longer because
it's taking too long it's creating too
much friction and maybe the board of
directors in the sea level are no longer
best positioned to decide on many things
they're deciding on today so I think
what we will be seeing in the next
decade to come and it's partly driven by
technology but in particularly driven by
AI technologies that there's going to be
a shift in power where and how decisions
are going to be taken and we will look
at organizations the way they are run
today the way they are structured today
they look like a dinosaur because they
are not really connected to what is
happening really in the marketplace in
real time so the sea level is facing a
big challenge of a how they're
connecting to the bottom and how the
information is Flowing as a basis for
them to take great decisions second
decision power is probably becoming
within an organization also more
distributed
so it's not going to be as centralized
as it used to be
and
the more important thing is and this is
very fundamental to free energy
governance
is communication
when you look into companies today and
even companies where I am on the board
of
it's frightening to see
how communication is a real problem
everybody has the best intentions to be
clear to be transparent but
communicating is many times also a
question of language
and if we do believe that in the future
the interface between the machine and
the human is going to be increasingly
important
we need to develop a language which
allows us to much better connect to the
machine
and that's where I believe the free
energy governance framework which is
built on the free energy principle which
is all about prediction error
minimization
when you start putting HD prediction and
prediction models at the center of what
it is about to run an organization take
the active inference Institute what is
your prediction model you do have a
prediction model which is actually your
world model and on a daily basis you are
generating predictions about what you
think should happen uh what is likely to
happen what interests the audience these
are all predictions you're you're you're
generating and eventually this team you
guys are applying your best judgment
of what you're doing many times you're
testing the predictions and the
predictions may actually give you
feedback which tell you you shouldn't be
doing this So eventually your judgment
will really matter but
what you do when you start adopting a
language of prediction error
minimization
I believe you become much more
performing because what you start doing
in a much more conscious way you start
measuring the performance of your
individual predictions which eventually
feed your decisions on the basis of your
very judgment and over time your
judgment improves as well because you're
you're testing and your measuring of
performance of predictions is getting
better
and when you do this and in in my book
in the later part of the book
when I've been trying to
relay a very theoretical concept more to
the world of practice I've been looking
at the budgeting process the budgeting
process is a great uh uh domain where
you have to make a projection a
prediction
about next year
and you make this prediction on facing
actually two fundamental questions what
is you control what you don't control
what is uh what you know and what you
don't know so there's a lot of unknowns
you have to deal with and when I'm
looking at a budgeting process I'm
dealing with a lot of unknowns what is
really critical for me is not the number
people put behind that unknown but is
the process they suggest of how they
turn the unknown into a known and it
always starts with very small steps
so I think organizations need to start
communicating much more in terms of
prediction models in predictions
falsifying those confirming those and
when you start articulating the strategy
or a vision you have
as a prediction model
and that there are predictions generated
by that prediction model and you empower
the community the the organization
through great and clear communication
to challenge your predictions you're
creating an a a very different culture
of how you engage the front line with
the key decision makers who at the end
of the day of course there's always a
small number of people who are
accountable for managing and allocating
the resources of a firm
so I think that's a critical hook
because a lot of
you know a lot of sea level people and
board members talk about uncertainty
but he is a really critical thing
first of all uncertainty is a very
subjective concept what your
uncertainties may not be mine or vice
versa so in my view when somebody says
the world is uncertain or unpredictable
I mean we all agree there is a lot of
things we don't know what's going to
happen tomorrow so in that regard
there's many many worlds that could
appear in that regard yes there is some
degree of unpredictability but if I talk
about uncertainty
of course there is uncertainty but
at the end using uncertainty and
unpredictability is really just an
admission of the very limitations of my
world model because
uncertainty is an incredibly Rich
training ground for my predictions
to eliminate and reduce uncertainty and
turn unknowns into notes and when you
look at organizations and I think
sometimes most of the time
sea level and board level
are not aware of the fact if the further
you go down in the organization to the
front line they have much more
intelligence and understand much better
how rules
are creating the source of inertia and
actually
masking and burying uncertainty and
don't make it available for prediction
testing and ultimately better decision
making so our challenge in today's world
with a lot of discontinuity a lot of
change happening for very understandable
reasons because the individual has more
power we have cheaper Technologies
available to create much more impact
we need to embrace uncertainty we should
not avoid uncertainty and today the
organizational Frameworks are not in
place to allow organizations to embrace
uncertainty because they don't know how
to talk in prediction and prediction
models and test those predictions I'm
sorry blue
sorry
just ask a quick follow-up question what
can you clarify what you mean by
discontinuity or discontinuous I mean I
think I have an idea but I would just
like to maybe have a more clear
you know I try to avoid the word
disruptive
but when you look at and you look in
management science Clayton Christian's
disruptive technology which is not
necessarily radical technology it's
technologies that
can change for example a cost factor and
the cost factor is so decisive that all
of a sudden
it changes the way business is being
done
and what is being deployed and whether
you you're still shipping something or
you're not shipping something or whether
it's uh it's I mean you could argue uh
to some degree
let's put the particular context of the
pandemic aside
but a valid question is the way
teams and zoom
have become so much part of our
day-to-day
engagement
I have been someone
who
has always preferred the physical touch
point and in my own company I have
offices in in in different parts and my
my Approach has always been I'm going to
be physically present in those offices
at least once a month as I tour them
I've changed this radically the pandemic
is over
so I definitely uh don't buy as many uh
flight tickets any longer
and this is it's not a strong example
but I do think that a lot of airlines
struggle with the fact that business
Travelers are not there the way they're
there there may be more recreational
Travelers and the planes continue to
impact but there's less planes we
shouldn't forget that either so has
video calling and and uh
um
created actually some discontinuity
on a massive scale that can disrupt
Industries
um so you do have uh this kind of
discontinuities they don't need to be
radical uh Innovations but they they
change on a massive scale the way things
are being done and there's obviously a
lot of examples that happen all the time
um that happens sometimes which are
beyond our
what we can see but there's a lot of
stuff which is happening behind the
scenes where things are so radically
changed that companies are from one day
to the next out of business
and I guess that's what I mean with this
continuity more in the term in view of
disruption but I don't like the term of
disruption
that that makes sense I think just to
I'm not sure if he had more you want to
give on this elevator pitch but I think
to kind of summarize but I think you're
saying or the essence of my takeaway is
you're really putting uncertainty at the
heart of the organization rather than
something that is to be worried about to
be anxious about you're really saying
hey this is an intrinsic part of being
an organization having a world model
there's nothing we can do about
uncertainty but we can manage it and we
can we can do that by making prediction
error as really the heart of how our
organization thinks about its business
uh absolutely and this comes back to the
active inference Institute because the
most most important words
in active inference is active
because you put action at the center of
what you do and it's the actions that
create your perceptions and not the
other way around and that's a
fundamental thing and you go into the
sea level they still do believe that
they perceive and then they act and
that's terrible because then you are
really a victim of whatever is happening
outside your control and the power of
the free energy governance framework and
obviously the free energy principle is
that you get actually into control and
the way you work yourself through to
reduce the unknowns and you can only do
this through the actions
and there was one question you had on
the on the first slide which I think was
question number six uh we don't have to
go back there but I it was related to
Silicon Valley and when you look at the
smaller a company is when you take uh
a startup business a startup business
usually does not have the challenge of
of uh uh top down by the map because
there's three guys sitting in a room and
uh there were many many heads uh at the
same time all they do share is one
purpose One mission and one big dream
and and and as a result of it almost in
a self-organizing way all the right
actions will fall into place because the
goal is so clear of what they want to
achieve
the problems start when the team starts
growing when things are being delegated
when all the sudden communication
becomes important when all of a sudden
there is a distance between where the
action is happening in the field and the
person
making the decisions about how financing
is being raised how it's being allocated
and what story is being taught
so
when you look at the very mature
companies in Silicon Valley and those
who have been successful and have kind
of shaped a big part of our life in the
last 10 20 years you look at an Uber you
look at a Facebook you look at the
Google is because these companies stayed
actually very true to their core and you
can look at that they fulfill all three
dimensions of the free energy governance
framework they make sure the way they
organize that a lot of decision power is
actually at the bottom they are not big
fans of pulling all the power to the top
they want to make sure that individual
entities can work operate the site and
be very agile and very fast so that's
already the first element the structural
element how you connect the top and the
button second element is the cognition
part
neither Google
no Uber nor Facebook any of these
companies
are doing market research when they
really started with what they want to do
as business to figure out is there a
market or whatever they create something
which they enact driven by a deep
passion many times a deep passion of
believing this is how the world should
work we will adapt the world to us it's
not us adapting to the world
and that is what makes these companies
incredibly strong because they're
creating their own equal niches when you
look at the the iPhone coming out in
2007 everybody was mocking it
Blackberry which some of you may not
know even at the time what was the
dominant communication device because it
had a great uh keyboard in all of this
to have a phone without a keyboard with
every disadvantage a low battery which
was literally putting everything
together but everything was really
sub-optimal
um one didn't give it much chance but
what
effectively at the time Steve Jobs as
the Visionary or representative of that
vision for a whole team articulated was
the phone will be a computer and it will
be a computer that can actually do
anything and you have it in your pocket
and that was a tremendous vision and
Nokia didn't have that vision and they
focused on the prime functionalities so
I think what these companies do is and
that's the second dimension of the free
energy governance framework they really
enact their own environments and the
third
one which is related to capabilities in
the free energy framework is and I have
related to this
um in the free energy
governance framework in my book I try to
be very specific but the capabilities
part I focus on is how and I'm always
focusing capabilities on the board level
and on the board level I look at how you
manage Duality and in business there is
two sets of dualities which explain
everything these are the two fundamental
sense and only those two sets the one is
how do you manage simultaneously
exploitation and exploration you have to
manage your existing business and
optimize it and take that cash flow
which is available and you have to work
on the future cash flow which doesn't
exist yet you don't have the products
yet and you have to find a way which is
very challenging lots of books have been
written about it of how you manage these
two things in parallel in the meantime
my view is these things happen actually
almost at once on top of each other
rather than being two separate
organizations
but there's many different views also
depending on the maturity of the company
the life cycle of the company what is
the better approach that's the first set
so first set between exploitation of
today's Cash Flow and developing through
exploration tomorrow's cash flow
the second set is a very important one
is the trade-off or the The Duality
between Financial control and strategic
control Financial control in this
context means
ebony how you buy other companies which
you're not doing in-house to accelerate
and to move forward strategic control is
really in-house Innovation so a company
and a board is continuously challenged
is there a sustainable balance between
in-house Innovation and external
Innovation or M A doesn't always have to
be about Innovation could be market
share
or a geographic expansion but
what is really important to understand
when a company relies too much
on financial control m a
its survival gets really threatened
because the more companies you buy
the more over a period of time your
in-house capability to innovate will
weaken and effectively you're losing
your strategic control now coming back
to the Silicon Valley companies what
they have done tremendously successful
whether it's a a meta Facebook Google
they have been continuously investing
they have been the biggest investor as a
as a percentage share of their revenues
they've invested in r d
but at the same time they buy a company
every month
so they keep this balance in a TR in an
incredible way
and that is in my view a tremendous
capability for a company to keep their
balance don't allow it going one way but
keep that balance so when you look at
the free energy governance framework
looking at really Silicon Valley is a
startup the question doesn't even arise
because everybody's sitting in one room
now you take this massive company some
of them are the biggest companies in the
world
like like apple and so on they have
mastered it in my view by
not being obsessed of how the top has to
control everything
understanding that we are much more
powerful as an organization if the
unknowns are being turned into nodes and
that those who are capable of doing it
are empowered and they're usually much
closer to the resource Market suppliers
Technologies clients in order to do so
so I do think in those companies you
find many facets of it which make it
very successful and I'm very convinced
that they are also the next companies
who are embracing artificial
intelligence
as a way of changing again
how organizations are structured how
they take decisions and how the power
may be shifting
but
and that was one of the questions you
asked me uh which is on the on the slide
is why being so obsessed with the board
actually I'm not obsessed with the board
as such but the reality is that the
board depending on you know the role of
the board varies many times from
countries from jurisdictions culture you
know what role they play but when you
look at a typical board
the CEO may be on the board in the U.S
the CEO usually is on the board the CEO
is actually usually also the chairman in
the rest of the world they strictly
separate this two-world CEO and chairman
but you will have the majority of the
board members being non-executives
and these non-executives have no role in
the day-to-day operation of the business
but they come and they Leverage The
expertise from different Industries and
uh overall their their their their
experience uh they they have accumulated
over uh usually a longer career
and the board because it is not
executive
is in my view uniquely positioned
not to get involved in the content
dimensions of the business the board
can't tell you you should be buying this
you should be doing this what the board
should be doing is to ensure that we
have a process that allows for free
energy governance to come to life
bottom and top properly connected
articulating prediction models having
the right language articulating
predictions and empowering the rest of
the organization to challenge those
predictions and the third one is where
the board has to self-evaluate are we
really keeping a good balance between
strategic control and financial control
and these are
a role which in my view cannot be
delegated to the CEO
and needs to come actually from a meter
organ which literally the board is to
ensure those processes and just make
sure
that they are in place and that they
stay alive
that that makes sense so if I understand
you correctly it's not to say that a
board is like intrinsically a part of
free energy governance but like we have
inherited these legal structures where
oftentimes for non-profits and C Corps
you need to have a board so you might as
well put to good use and a nice
attribute of a board is that it's
separate from the rest of the
organization and that means can play
this kind of unique and special role in
free energy governance does that
characterize what you're saying
correctly absolutely and if you look at
the Dao I mean effectively it's a it's a
it's a software and it's a it's a
Contracting I mean a smart Contracting
in a certain way so what you should be
doing you should be because in the Dao
the governance Dimension is not about
content I mean it's not about saying you
know you should be going left you should
be going right the real question is
are you following the right process
when certain things should happen or
they shouldn't happen and that in my
view is is is is is for a board
should be the guardian
of
institutionalizing and of keeping alive
self-organizing mechanisms
as I describe them with the free energy
governance framework and I think in the
Dao you may actually write this into the
software the way those things it's the
language the communication the way
actually uh what information can
actually take decisions in in in in and
has the right judgment
that that makes sense and I'm actually
curious this might be a hard question I
think will be part of the reason it's
hard is very contextually dependent but
I'm wondering if you could have your
pick up like a a different governance
structure right maybe it's not the board
but something else that would be more uh
fine-tuned and appropriate for figuring
energy governance and like you can have
any legal structure you wanted
are there things that you would change
about the board or maybe it's like just
to knock the board at all it's a
different kind of entity that you would
think would be more appropriate for
pre-industry governance
you know I do I do think
that the power of
the board and if you think about it it's
funny you know
historically it was never one person
aboard it's always like two people three
people so I do think the idea of having
a small group of people coming together
that are not involved in the day-to-day
business as a management team
to deliberate and think about very key
decisions about
which concern the whole firm
uh is in my view Irreplaceable and I
really do believe in this now
what we do see however is that some
boards are completely irrelevant some
boards are source of inertia and
we we and a lot of the corporate
governance literature is about how do
you make the board really effective then
it comes into diversity discussions and
all of this I don't think that is really
the key
um it really comes down to uh I'm not a
big fan of the of the
diversity in terms of stereotypical
diversity you know to say oh we should
have uh uh you know for example the
Nordic countries in Europe have made it
the law that a certain number of board
members need to be female
and right now it's it's it's really
crazy because they don't find enough
women so so who are prepared to go on
the board even and who are qualified to
go on the board and uh it's a it's a
it's a it's a I think that is the wrong
way I think what you want is you want to
constantly self-evaluate a support to
ensure that you have the right expertise
the right qualities on the board to
steer the company through its next
challenges
got I see so instead of like a top-down
mandated
version of like hey this is the kind of
diversity you have that should actually
be an internalized process where you
would internally be saying like hey
actually we don't have representation
from these groups that's actually
probably hampering our decision making
processes in these ways let's
intentionally create diversity to create
new cognitive capabilities on our board
does that capture that right I would put
yeah I would put the emphasis on the
cognitive uh Dimensions having said this
see I'm on the board of a company in
Switzerland
um which is quite big
has many thousands of employees is
involved around the globe okay and I'm
always embarrassed when I look at the
website and you have four male whites
guys on the board
and this is a company which is globally
active we have a very important part of
women in our Workforce uh and I don't
think the board represents this so I do
think the board has to represent
in some way also the world you represent
as a business and I I think that board
needs to change in terms of diversity
but the diversity shouldn't be just
changed for the sake of diversity it
should bring in as you rightly set the
cognitive diversity uh at the same time
but we all know
sometimes and that's I guess that's what
the lawmakers
imply uh the cognitive diversity is many
times related to the stereotypical
diversity
um I'm not saying anything else to add
to this I do want to switch gears a
little bit because we have about 10
minutes left
and so something you're talking about
too is like you're envisioning a very
different version of what a a board
looks like and get to the right slide so
both for like implementing free energy
governance from the perspective of being
inside a board but then also within the
entire organization like it's a very
different way that especially a board
needs to operate
and I know that you're on the board of
several companies you're also a leader
of several companies as well I'm kind of
curious how you think about the
resistance that you've encountered in
implementing free energy governance both
within the board and outside of the
board as well and so for example like
I've had personal experiences with this
as well not necessarily implementing
free energy governance but also
implementing things that are less
hierarchical more of a collective sense
making process where we're not top down
deciding the strategy but we're more
collectively through a sense making
process understand you know Finding what
that purpose is and I've often found
that can be very disorienting for folks
and a lot of fear and uncertainty arises
during that process and a lot of
resistance comes during that process as
well I would imagine that you would
encounter similar things in implementing
free energy governance both within the
board and then within the larger
organization so I'm kind of curious
about types of resistance that you found
and how you've kind of overcome that
resistance in your own organizations
yeah good very good question I mean
effectively it's it's a question or this
this whole topic touches upon let's be
very precise how do you make actually
free energy governance work in an
organization give me some very precise
tools if I was interested now in
Bridging the bottom in the top uh uh uh
and doing all these things uh what
should I do give me a plan uh give me
some inspiration what other companies
have been doing that's what I'm looking
at putting together now through a
research project I'm undertaking to to
look at companies uh they may not call
it free energy governance but they're
dealing precisely with those issues and
what they have been doing but I want to
add So my answer will be twofold I'm
gonna answer first of all was your
question and then come actually to what
should be done because the two are kind
of related in a certain way the
resistance I see in in boards is when
you look at a board of directors
it's a really very strange group of
people
because they
most of the time the recruitment of
those people is coming through
connections
I mean of course many times you do have
a Headhunter saying like we need a board
member can you find us somebody
interesting and somebody comes and that
that happens I'm sure I don't know what
the percentage is but a fair share of
board positions are being done this way
but then most of the time the board
members obviously know a lot of board
members and they say look this is a
great person that person can join the
board has these and these qualifications
so what happens at the end that the
board comes together a little bit as a
club
so there is in the board
uh and by the way there's a lot of
research which also says it's quite
important that the board members get
along very well so that there is a is a
good climate Okay on the board table
uh it's a group of people who share a
lot of responsibility
what I have
seen over the time is that because of
these things and also because many times
there can be a lot of pressure on the
board taking decisions in particular the
moment of Crisis and there's an
additional communication challenge
because I be the public vis-a-vis the
employee Force so when you face these
challenges it brings you obviously
together it's like a like a family in
the forest facing a a challenge to fight
you come even closer together and you
you you you you tend in the context of
the of the board you tend to become a
little bit introverted and that's a real
problem because you start
again it's skilled incompetence it's
counter productive to what you're
actually trying to achieve you become
further removed from the rest of the
organization
you start inviting people to make
presentations then you close the doors
again you stay amongst yourself and I
think you're going to be Hostage to a
lot of blind spots to a lot of buyers
towards a lot of patent recognition
which nothing is always the same
and you start becoming a little bit too
overconfident the way you can take
decisions and my Approach has been
um and that's a problem I do think that
every board what I've just described
suffers to a certain degree from that
that that pathology
and
that makes it sometimes very difficult
because when you think about it the free
energy governance framework is all about
how the boards opens how the board
communicates how the board connects and
picks up the intelligence which is at
the bottom
and now we come to very concrete
measures of what you can do in order to
actually change this and there are and I
have to say to answer your question
I have been practicing free energy
governance as a CEO
making and the way I run the company and
the way the flow of information is
generated the way decision power is
distributed that the company is really
empowered to make judgment calls and
execute them and that not the top
becomes a bottleneck so I'm pretty good
at that when I look at my board and my
own company which is a pretty strong
board with very strong people and strong
backgrounds very serious business people
I find it very difficult for example to
say hey on the website why don't you put
next to your photo
a sentence which explains what's your
contribution to this company why are you
on the board
I think that's a question everybody
should answer and I think it makes all
of a sudden a board member much more
accessible to the rest of the
organization because if somebody says to
me like they're responsible for China
and I'm I'm involved in China then there
is a guy or a woman I should be
contacting and and maybe share some
ideas so I think that's a way of the
board opening up I think a board member
should have on their website
stating in one sentence why they're on
that board and what their contribution
is to the company
from which angle they're coming that
opens up second
which is a great way and I've been
practicing this quite a bit
is creating deep Dives where you take
people very Junior people
on a specific topic where you believe
these Junior people middle layer people
executive leadership people together
with selected board members not the
whole board create a deep dive around
the topic no presentations and just Deep
dive into a topic sharing actually what
experiences they are to advance the
topic and that usually is an incredible
experience by the end of the of the
meeting you don't know who's a board
member and who's a junior guy because
you don't come with this like come in
here make me a PowerPoint presentation
I'm listening to you and then I will
judge and come with all my experience
you have to kill all of this
the other element which I really like
and I'm looking much deeper into it and
there are a number of big companies who
have been doing it
is creating Shadow boards so now what
you're doing is you're looking at the
closer to the front lines of really high
potential
people Talent
who form a board
which is
holding a board meeting at the very same
time the main board is holding its board
meeting they have more or less the same
documentation the same agenda points
and they take decisions as if they were
the board
they Define agenda items for the next
board meeting and all of a sudden you're
creating a group of people
at the closer to the front line who have
to
delve into the topics there must be
obviously seen enough that they can be
entrusted and that they are capable of
understanding all the issues and and
assuming that role in a way of not just
looking at their domain where they're
acting maybe but looking at the whole
organization because that's a challenge
for the board too you have to really
understand how to relate and how to
respect a lot of interacting parts of a
company
and then you compare afterwards the
shadow board what they have discussed
how they have decided that's a
tremendous input of Frontline
information of intelligence feeding into
the main board and possibly determining
future agenda items
oh man there's a lot of Juicy
action-oriented things I would love to
spend the next four hours going into
unfortunately we're at the top of the
hour and so uh hopefully we can have you
back and we can go deeper into some of
these especially the practice oriented
recommendations we'd love to explore
that more but before we we wrap up and
be respectful of each other's time
curious if anyone has any final closing
thoughts comments
um Reflections questions before we wrap
up
I appreciate uh Tyler and blue that
you're leading this series we're going
to continue the regular more section
oriented videos keep a space open for
others to come in and range freely and
Bijan thanks again for joining your
welcome back anytime
yeah I think look thank you for inviting
me I'm I'm very honored that you took
the book and you're dedicating the time
to it I do really believe not because I
wrote the book obviously it's a very
theoretical contribution a more
practical orientation a contribution
should follow but I do believe and I
guess that's why also Carl Frist decided
to write the forward uh and also Connie
helfert from that was uh wrote the
forward is because I do think this is
the beginning of changing things and as
I think Daniel said it at the at the
beginning uh or I think it was blue uh
saying uh this is something the actively
inference Institute should be looking at
and being inspired by how you uh design
governments
thanks again until next time
thank you very well thank you so thanks
for Sean all right thank you thank you
very much bye-bye